Shavua tov שבוע טוב, Shavua tov, Chodesh tov חודש טוב. Chodesh tov.
We’ll have to...
so here’s a question. Is there a mitzvah מצוה mitzvah of Marbin
b’Simcha מרבין בשמחה Marbin b’Simcha on Adar Rishon אדר ראשון Adar Rishon
when it’s not even yet ela Adar אלא אדר? ela Adar? Rosh
Chodesh Adar ראש חודש אדר Rosh Chodesh Adar without that being yet
Adar Rishon אדר ראשון. Adar Rishon. So you can decide that. Alright,
anyway. What? Lamed Shevat ל' שבט. Lamed Shevat.
Right, it’s Lamed Shevat ל' שבט. Lamed Shevat. Okay, bottom of... today’s
daf דף daf is Peh Daled פ"ד Peh Daled and we pick
up on the very bottom of Peh Gimmel Amud Bet פ"ג עמוד
ב'. Peh Gimmel Amud Bet. Mishe-nashkho kelev shoteh מי שנשכו כלב שוטה,
Mishe-nashkho kelev shoteh, somebody who was bit by a rabid dog. Okay,
so the Mishnah משנה Mishnah moved on from Yom Kippur יום כיפור
Yom Kippur to the fact that you can eat non-kosher food if
necessary for a health issue or certainly a risk of life issue.
And then there was a discussion though of what constitutes a legitimate
refuah רפואה, refuah, the practice of feeding the lobe, the liver, of
a rabid dog to the person who was bit by the rabid
dog. So the Chachamim חכמים Chachamim say... so Matya ben Charash מתיא
בן חרש Matya ben Charash says you can do it and the
Chachamim חכמים Chachamim say that it's a legitimate refuah רפואה... refuah... Matya
ben Charash מתיא בן חרש, Matya ben Charash, excuse me, and the
Chachamim חכמים Chachamim do not allow it.
Is this in reality rabies? I believe it is.
Rabies? I believe it is.
The number of cases of someone who’s actually got rabies case is
to be recovered in the entire history of the human race is
one. And that’s within the past ten years.
Wow. Really? Everybody who actually gets rabies dies as a result? They
came...
one woman, they figured out a treatment for her within the past
ten years and she is still alive. Wow. They’ll probably try it
in this her. But it is 100%.
So when you’re bit by a rabid dog the point is you
need to get a treatment before the rabies actually develops.
Correct. That's a vaccine. That's within the past hundred years.
So the vaccine prevents what?
Prevents the rabies from developing.
Rabies is what? It’s a virus. Uh-huh.
And it... I see. It's a virus that affects essentially all mammals.
Uh-huh. And wow. If you actually... if the rabies disease develops until...
except for that one case. Wow. And how quickly does that happen?
It takes... yeah, something like that, yeah.
Wow.
Wow. So you have to get the shot... you have to get
the shot right away.
Wow. In a series of shots. Okay. Ten days...
something like that.
Wow.
And the shots are not pleasant.
Tanu Rabanan תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabanan, chamishah devarim neemru b'kelev shoteh חמישה
דברים נאמרו בכלב שוטה. chamishah devarim neemru b'kelev shoteh.
Five things, five identifiers were said regarding a rabid dog. Pee patuach
פיו פתוח, pee patuach, its mouth is open, v’riro notef ורירו נוטף,
v’riro notef, right, well that’s it, v’riro notef ורירו נוטף, v’riro notef,
the spittle is like you know dripping and... v'oznav srukhot ואזניו סרוחות
v'oznav srukhot
and its ears are drooping, v’znavo munach al yarkhotav וזנבו מונח על
ירכותיו, v’znavo munach al yarkhotav,
its tail is like between its legs on its thighs, v'mehalech b’tzidei
drakhim ומהלך בצידי דרכים v'mehalech b’tzidei drakhim and it walks at the
sides of the roads,
not in the middle of the road. V’yesh omrim af noveach v’ein
kolo nishmah ויש אומרים אף נובח ואין קולו נשמע. v’yesh omrim af
noveach v’ein kolo nishmah.
Some say it barks and it cannot be heard when it’s barking,
like it’s a silent bark. Mimai havei ממאי הוי? Mimai havei? Now
what
is... what leads to a dog to be rabid? So Rav רב
Rav amar nashim kashfaniyot mesakhakot bo אמר נשים כשפניות משחקות בו. amar
nashim kashfaniyot mesakhakot bo. Rav רב Rav says women who do witchcraft
play, you know, play with it. Basically Rashi רש"י Rashi sounds like
they use it to experiment or they use it to demonstrate their
ability, so they do their witchcraft on the dog. U’shmuel ושמואל U’shmuel
amar ruach ra'ah shoreh alav אמר רוח רעה שורה עליו. amar ruach
ra'ah shoreh alav. The...
an evil spirit, it's about, you know, these demons and demonic and
evil spirits, so that is seizing the dog. Mai beiniyu מאי בינייהו?
Mai beiniyu? What difference does it make what you think is the
source of it? Ika beiniyu איכא בינייהו, Ika beiniyu, top of Peh
Daled Amud Aleph פ"ד עמוד א', Peh Daled Amud Aleph, l’miktelei b’davar
hanizrak למקטליה בדבר הנזרק. l’miktelei b’davar hanizrak.
If you want to try to kill the dog, should you try
to kill it at a distance or not? So if you think
it's a ruach ra'ah רוח רעה, ruach ra'ah, then you have to
keep your distance, even getting close even if it doesn't bite you,
the ruach ra'ah רוח רעה ruach ra'ah might get to you. But
if it's about this witchcraft, interestingly, maybe witchcraft is also contagious, you
know, the effects of the spell, but apparently not. Apparently if it's
witchcraft there's no problem about drawing close, but if it's an evil
spirit there is. So the question would be whether you would have
to try to kill it by throwing something, by a projectile. Would
that be the way to kill it rather than getting too close?
I will mention by the way about that that it's worth noting
because we just recently read Parshat Yitro פרשת יתרו Parshat Yitro and
a common read of a pasuk פסוק pasuk is based on Rashi
רש"י Rashi which is not the pshat פשט pshat read of the
pasuk פסוק pasuk where it says if somebody gets... goes to Har
Sinai הר סיני, Har Sinai, what do the Torah say? Skol yisakel
o yaroh yiyareh סקול יסקל או ירה יירה. skol yisakel o yaroh
yiyareh.
So Rashi רש"י Rashi says you do skilah סקילה skilah or yaroh
yiyareh ירה יירה. yaroh yiyareh. Rashi רש"י Rashi says like to cast
over a cliff because that’s according to halakha הלכה, halakha, you know,
the... you know,
well first of all it's also the whole Seir l’Azazel שעיר לעזאזל
Seir l’Azazel image. But anyway, that's the way Rashi רש"י Rashi understands
it that it's a... yaroh yiyareh ירה יירה yaroh yiyareh means cast
person off the cliff. But the pshat פשט pshat is if somebody
gets close to Har Sinai הר סיני, Har Sinai, what are you
supposed to do? You're not allowed to get close to Har Sinai
הר סיני Har Sinai to stop the guy. So how do you
stop him? So you either throw stones at him or you shoot
arrows at him. So that's the way you stop him without you
yourself getting close. So same... anyway, it was just reminded of that
because here the only way to stop the dog is through projectile,
you can't actually draw closer.
And then the... world more about the technology has...
Not invent, but that's what you have to do. Okay. תניא כוותיה
דשמואל, Tanya kvatei d'Shmuel, we taught like שמואל: Shmuel: כשהורגו אין הורגו
אלא בדבר הנזרק, keshehorgo ein horgo ela b'davar hanizrak,
when you have to kill a rabid dog, you only kill it
from a—distance? That's an interesting question, possibly, though we're not discussing it,
from a distance by throwing projectiles. Might depend on a סוגיא בשבת
sugya b'Shabbat about also when מזיקין mazikin are running after you; if
they're not actually running after you, you know, do you have to
be חושש choshesh that they will attack or not? So it might
be under some circumstances you could do it even on יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur. Anyway, you do it by throwing a projectile, not by
getting too close because of the way the גמרא Gemara is explaining
this concern of witchcraft, or excuse me, of the רוח רעה, ruach
ra'ah, of the evil spirit. Okay. דחייף ביה מסתכן, d'chaif bei mistaken,
if you rub up against this dog, you are in danger. דנכית
ליה מאית, d'nachit lei mayis,
if the dog bites you, you'll die. דחייף ביה מסתכן, d'chaif bei
mistaken,
if you rub up against it, you're in danger. מאי תקנתיה, mai
taknatei, what should you do if that happens? How do you protect
yourself from the—from, you know, from the ensuing danger? So if you
actually did rub up against it, נשלח מאני, nishlach manei,
cast off your clothes, ונרהט, v'nirat, and run. רב הונא בריה דרב
יהושע Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua חף ביה, chaf bei, רב הונא
Rav Huna the son of רב יהושע Rav Yehoshua
rubbed up against a rabid dog, חד מינייהו, chad mineihu,
one of them, one of the rabid dogs rubbed up against him
בשוקא b'shuka in the marketplace. שלחינהו למאניה, shalchinhu l'manei,
he cast off his clothes, ורהט, v'rahat, and he ran. אמר, amar,
he said, קיימתי בעצמי, kiyamti b'atzmi, I fulfilled with myself החכמה תחיה
בעליה, hachochma techaye v'aleha,
wisdom will keep its owners alive. I knew what to do and
therefore I was saved. We had that פסוק pasuk before about eating
a, you know, the sweet figs if a person was seized by
בולמוס, bulmos, he knew where to go to get the sweet figs.
Here you know what to do if a rabid dog rubs up
against you. So I guess they figured that the contagion would adhere
to the clothes because he's rubbing up against your clothes, so strip
your clothes and get away from it and that'll—and that'll save you.
דנכית ליה מאית, d'nachit lei mayis, if it bites you, you'll die.
מאי תקנתיה, mai taknatei, what is the fix? What's the—what's the fix?
What do you do if it actually happens? So
אמר אביי, amar Abaye, אביי Abaye says, ניתי משכא
דאפא דדכרא, neitei mashka d'apa d'dichra, get the leather of a male
אפא, apa, a hyena, of a male hyena, ונכתב עליה, v'nichtav alei,
and write on this leather: אנא פלניא בר פלניתא, ana Planya bar
Planisa,
I so-and-so, the son of, your mother's name, אמשכא דאפא דכרא כתיבנא
עלך, amashka d'apa dichra ksivna alach,
on the leather of a male hyena I am writing on you,
you know, I am writing on
you on the leather of this male
hyena, and here's what—and then you continue to write the following: כנתי
כנתי קלירוס. kanti kanti kliros. Okay,
so which is obviously some type of incantation. ואמרי לה, v'amri lei,
some say, קנדי קנדי קלורוס, kandi kandi kloros, יה יה השם צבאות,
Ya Ya Hashem Tzeva'ot,
God, God, God of Hosts, אמן אמן סלה. Amen Amen Sela. Okay,
ונשלחינהו למאניה, v'nishalchinhu l'manei,
and then cast off your clothes after you wrote this on the
hyena's leather, cast off your clothes, ולקברינהו, v'likbrinhu, and bury it בי
קברי bei kivrei in a cemetery.
Some have the גרסא girsa in a cemetery on the crossroads. עד
תריסר ירחי שתא, ad treisar yarchei shata,
and for 12 months. ונפקינהו, v'nafkinhu,
then at the end of 12 months take out your—dig up your
clothes, ונקלינהו בתנורא, v'naklinhu b'tanura,
burn them in an oven, ונבדרינהו לקטמי v'navdarinhu l'kitmei אפרשת דרכים, aparsat
drachim,
and scatter the ashes on a crossroads. והנך תריסר ירחי, v'hanach treisar
yarchei, and those interim 12 months, what are you doing to protect
yourself? Because I guess making it into ashes and scattering it is
the end of the רפואה, refuah, burn it. Okay, apparently that finishes
the רפואה, refuah, so during those 12 months you're still in danger.
So what do you do during those 12 months? כי שתי מיא
לא לישתי אלא בגובתא דנחשא, ki shati maya lo lishti ela b'guvta
d'nachsha,
when you drink water, only drink it through a copper pipe, a
copper tube. דילמא חזי בבואה דשידא, dilma chazi bavuah d'shida,
lest if you drink it in some other vessel, you will see
the image of the shade of
the—spirit? Demon, demon, and ויסתכן, v'yistaken, and you'll be in danger. So
obviously this had to do—I mean this ties in, I didn't—I didn't
double-check against it, but there are those famous אגדתות aggadatos at the
beginning of ברכות Berachos that deals with seeing the מזיקין mazikin and
seeing the שדים shedim and also deals with various types of metal
tubes. So somehow the metal tubing will protect the shade from getting
into the water and through the water getting into you. So this
presumably is following שמואל's Shmuel idea that this is based on רוח
רעה. ruach ra'ah. One minute.
Okay. כי הא דאבא בר מרתא, ki ha d'Abba bar Marta, like
אבא בר מרתא, Abba bar Marta, דהוא אבא בר מניומי, d'hu Abba
bar Minyumi, אבא בר מניומי, Abba bar Minyumi, עבדא ליה אימיה גובתא
דדהבא. avda lei imei guvta d'dahava.
His mother made for him a golden tube in which to drink
his liquid. I don't know why, because when—was it when he was
bit by a rabid dog or is just in general to protect
him from שדים? shedim? Who knows? Anyway, this
is the—this is the
גמרא.
Gemara. And I checked there've now been seven people who survived in
the last few years
of actually having rabies.
Having rabies. Yeah, but how can you be alive 12 months later?
Well, that's what Charlie said, just because you're bit by a rabid
dog doesn't mean you contract rabies. Not
everybody who has HIV actually gets AIDS. You know, so just because
you have the virus doesn't
mean you're a carrier. Right. Right. Okay, all right. Anyway, moving on.
ואמר המתיא, vo-amar Ha-matya,
so that's the whole identifying of the issue of the rabid dog.
But again, the important point for us להלכה le-halacha is that if
הלכה halacha says that if it's a פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh you
can do what you need to do to violate שבת, Shabbos, violate
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, violate כשרות. kashrus. What types of רפואות, refuos,
who gets to determine what is considered a legitimate רפואה? refuah? You
know, and to what degree does הלכה halacha have to get, you
know, get to have a say in it? Obviously הלכה halacha does
have a say, you know, it's debated, it seems like the debate
is not that רב מתיא בן חרש Rav Matya ben Charash is
saying, look, whatever people think works we have to just, you know,
accept. It seems like he's just has a different assessment whether or
not this is potentially effective or not. It is interesting because we
before learned yesterday that in terms of the assessment of the חולה,
choleh, not only about how they're feeling, but what they need, the
חולה choleh says I need to eat and the doctors say you
don't, that the חולה choleh trumps. So here, if a חולה choleh
says I need to do this רפואה refuah and we actually say,
yeah, that רפואה refuah is just בבא מעשיות bubba meises and נארישקייט,
narrishkeit, you know, that there is some possibility that we could disallow
it, you know, because we we object, you know, we'll say objectively
it doesn't, you know, it's not a, you know, an effective or
meaningful רפואה. refuah. So it is an interesting question as I said,
in particular nowadays holistic medicine and other types of things, somebody says
I think I need to do this, you know, what's the rabbi's
role in saying, well I, you know, I don't think that that's
a good רפואה refuah or not? Yes.
So I mean aside from the whole שד shed analogy and I
mean they knew that there were things they couldn't see that somehow
were affecting their health. Right. So can we read these in a
way the perspective of let's say Rabbi Slifkin that says, listen, the
חכמים chakhamim participated in what they considered to be the current medical
knowledge and if our medical knowledge supersedes theirs, there are even הלכתי
halakhic implications?
Yeah, I mean the רמב"ם, Rambam, right, the רמב"ם Rambam basically dealing
with in general these types of issues already the גאונים Geonim say,
you know, we're not we're not constrained by or we don't follow
the רפואות refuos in the גמרא. Gemara. You know, what now they
don't exactly give the logic why not, but they basically say, yeah,
that's, you know, we don't go by that. So there's two basic
ways of explaining why we don't go by that. The רמב"ם Rambam
says, I think what we would all say, which is the rabbis,
you know, were not scientists, they knew the science of their time,
so you cannot expect to get from them whether it's about questions
about medical science or about astronomy or about anything else. They were
limited by the science of their time and if we know better
now then that science doesn't dictate for us, end of story, that's
simple. The פרום frummer way of saying it, now that's one thing
when the גמרא Gemara is giving you medical advice, it's another thing
when the גמרא Gemara uses science to be the basis of הלכה
halacha and then if we say they got the science wrong and
we know better, how does that impact הלכה? halacha? That's like a
separate conversation. But certainly if all they're doing is giving you medical
advice, to say, yeah, we can dismiss it because we can say
they were limited by that their medical knowledge. That's what רמב"ם Rambam
says. The פרום frummer approach is to say the answer that the
גאונים Geonim come up with, which is the what I would call
the strategy of dealing with the fact that our reality is not,
you know, what we experience, right, what we experience, what the גמרא
Gemara says that, you know, our sort of empirical, you know, evidence
and our experience goes against what the גמרא Gemara says, is rather
than saying the גמרא Gemara got it wrong, it's to say that
our reality has shifted, נשתנה הטבע. nishtanu ha-teva. And that way you're
rather than pretending like oh yes this all works, you're you can
accept the fact that it doesn't work, but you don't have to
say the rabbis got anything wrong, you could just say that the
world changed, nature changed, reality changed. And that's like the more the
פרום frummer strategy, it allows you to deal with the fact that
it's not the same without having to concede that the rabbis, you
know, got it wrong. Yes.
Isn't following רמב"ם Rambam less פרום frum than following someone else?
It's less no no, it's not less פרום frum in the sense
that רמב"ם Rambam in general, it's less פרום frum the general approach,
I don't necessarily by פרום frum mean right, or I mean פרום
frum in this sort of sociological פרום frummy sense, it's because it
because it acknowledges that חז"ל Chazal got something wrong and for some
people that's a very dangerous idea. So it's a safer idea to
say they didn't get anything wrong. Yes.
The other thing and I haven't seen a chance to look at
this, scientists get things wrong all the time today. scientists get things
wrong all the time today, in our times. But it isn't necessarily
that they were doing anything wrong. They were using the information they
had.
I understand. I understand. But for for a lot of people to
suggest that the what the rabbis are on the מדריגה madriga of
the scientists? I mean the rabbis are you know the rabbis. So
how could they get anything wrong? So for some people suggesting no
matter you know putting them within sort of normal human context and
limiting them to the knowledge of their time and allowing for error
is a very dangerous idea because then it starts raising questions about
well how do we trust anything they say? So that's why for
some people it's safer to say they had everything right and and
the world around them changed. Okay, anyway, it's a larger conversation. Let's
go back to the גמרא. Gemara. ועוד אמר רב מתיה. V'od amar
Rav Matya. So also says רב מתיה, Rav Matya, this is about
the second point not about the rabid dog but about the issue
about somebody with a throat, a sore throat or some problem in
the throat, he can drink a medicine, a strep throat on שבת,
Shabbos, which would seem to be should be relatively undebated and we'll
take a look in the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא's Gemara going to
move around to that and then it got to the very general
statement that anything that is פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh overrides שבת. Shabbat.
So רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, so we're going to start by telling
some stories about people with sore throat. רבי יוחנן חש בצפדנא. Rabbi
Yochanan chash bitzapidna. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan had scurvy. What exactly is
scurvy? Vitamin C deficiency. What are the how does it manifest itself?
It's on your skin I think.
Is it like scabs and whatever?
You lose your teeth.
Okay. Okay. Alright. Doesn't start yet with a throat issue though we'll
see a throat issue's coming up. רבי יוחנן חש בצפדנא. Rabbi Yochanan
chash bitzapidna. He had scurvy. אזל גבי דהיא מטרוניתא. Azal gabbe d'hai
matronisa. He went to a matron which is a non-Jewish woman a
particular you know of status a particular like important woman who was
apparently knew these you know was a herbalist or was a doctor
of sorts and עבדא ליה מילתא avda lei milsa and she made
for him some type of a potion some type of a you
know of a medicine
חמשה ומעלי שבתא Chamsha u-mali shabta she made it for him on
Thursday and on Friday and he you know he took it and
it was hopefully helping him get better.
אמר לה בשבתא מאי? Amar lah b-shabta mai? So he said to
her what am I going to do on שבת? Shabbos? I can't
come to you. Exactly, he's asking the doctor essentially. He's asking every
day I come to you you provide this with to me what
can I what am I going to do on שבת? Shabbos? I'm
not going to be able to travel to you what what what
should I do? No no no no no he wasn't saying can
I take it.
You have been providing me the medicine I can't come on
שבת Shabbos what should I do?
So אמרה ליה amra lei so she said to him לא צריכת.
lo tzrichas. No don't worry you won't need to take the medicine
you already took it two days. אם איצטריכנא מאי? Im itztrichna mai?
But if he says but look let's say I start getting the
symptoms again and I do need to do it still that's not
an answer what should I do? So אמרה ליה amra lei so
she said to him she didn't want to give away any trade
secrets so she said to him אישתבע לי דלא מגלית. ishtaba li
d'lo maglis. You have to take an oath to me that if
I tell you how to make this medicine you won't tell anybody
else. אישתבע לה לאלהא דישראל לא מגלינא. ishtaba leh l'elaha d'yisrael lo
maglina. He took an oath and said to the God of Israel
I will not reveal this. נפק Nafik and then so she told
him. She told him it was שבת Shabbos so what did he
do? Instead of giving the regular דרשה drasha on the פרשה, parsha,
נפק דרשה בפירקא. nafik darsha b-pirka. He used the opportunity when everybody
was in שול shul to tell the whole community here's what you
have to do if you get scurvy or it's a פיקוח נפש
pikuach nefesh issue or whatever it was he wanted that everybody should
know the medicine to you know good for their health. So of
course so the גמרא Gemara says how could he do that? והא
אישתבע לה? V'ha ishtaba lah? Didn't he take an oath? He's violating
his oath? So the גמרא Gemara says let's no here's what he
meant. He meant לאלהא דישראל לא מגלינא הא לעמא דישראל מגלינא. l'elaha
d'yisrael lo maglina ha l'ama d'yisrael maglina. He said to the God
of Israel I won't reveal it so they're saying I won't reveal
it to the God of Israel I'll reveal it to the people
of Israel. So he obviously you know said it in a way
that allowed him an out. So the גמרא Gemara says ואיכא חילול
השם. v'ika chillul Hashem. Okay but technically he didn't violate his oath
but he's making it look like it's a חילול השם. chillul Hashem.
It's a desecration of God's name. He's making it look like to
the non-Jews that he basically violated an oath taken in the name
of God. People will think a that he tricked them that he
tricked her and b that he doesn't respect God that he's willing
to violate an oath to God. This by the way I should
say you know normally חילול השם chillul Hashem is used in a
sort of general sense anything that brings disrepute to God's name but
here there's a sense of חילול השם chillul Hashem because God's name
right was taken in an oath and there's a violation of that
oath. So anyway how about that that's how it appears. So the
גמרא Gemara says דמגלי לה מעיקרא. d'magli lah mei-ikara. No he after
she told him he said thank you very much by the way
you should realize here's what my oath actually meant. So there wasn't
a חילול השם chilul Hashem that she didn't think he violated the
oath. She still thought he was a sneaky Jew that he managed
to deceive her and get her to reveal it, but at least
she didn't think he actually violated the oath. So I don't know
how that's not a חילול השם. chilul Hashem. It's a different type
of a חילול השם. chilul Hashem. But so that's a fascinating and
slightly disturbing story, but talks about, you know, how important they felt
the health issues were, that it was worth, it was worth whatever
the cost was here in order to protect the people and share
this with the people. It goes like those old questions that they
ask, you know, isn't that famous thing they do when they're sort
of giving like tests to people and trying to sort of figure,
to, you know, see like how they, like how they think, like
their ethical statement, their ethical
systems? They give the, you know, the classic question is, you know,
you have, you know, you have a child and he's deathly sick
and he's dying, but the, you know, medicine costs like a thousand
dollars and you don't have any money, and you know, the pharmacist
has it and he won't sell it to you, what do you
do? Right? So, you know, do you go ahead and you like
basically try to steal it? Do you accept the consequences? Do you
whatever? Anyway, so based on how people answer the question shows the,
you know, their way of sort of ethical thinking, of moral thinking.
Anyway, so it's sort of like this, how much, how far are
you willing to go to violate certain, you know, other laws of
בין אדם לחברו bein adam l'chaveiro and how people's impression of you
and so on for the sake of protecting people. Of course, that
scenario's a little different, there it's like an immediate פיקוח נפש. pikuach
nefesh. Here it's like nobody in the community is sick, and when
they are sick presumably they could go to this woman, you know,
but still this idea of like spreading, you know, for the sake
of spreading. Maybe the better example would be what's his name? Would
be Snowden, right? Secret knowledge, but what does it mean to share
secret knowledge, classified knowledge that maybe you don't have a right to
share but you think is in the better interest, best interests of,
you know, the larger society? Right? He's sharing in the law of
unintended consequences.
They wrote Snowden down there in the footnote? Artscroll? Artscroll records according
to some
אמוראים, Amoraim, she committed suicide because she was distressed that her exclusive
remedy was now freely available to the public. But some אמוראים Amoraim
assert that she converted to Judaism because she was so impressed that
Rabbi Yochanan publicized the cure without making any money
from it.
Ah, so
he didn't make money from it. So then like Snowden, right? Just
do it for the better of the community, not to make a
profit. Consequences of Obamacare. Okay. All right, moving on. All right, so
the גמרא Gemara says now, מאי עבדא ליה? mai avda leh? Now
look, if Rabbi Yochanan went to all that effort to take this
oath and then reveal it, let's figure out what the, what the,
what the medicine was. So what did she do for him? אמר
רב אחא בריה דרב אמי, Amar Rav Acha brei d'Rav Ami, מי
שעור, mei se'or,
here is the recipe,
like a yeast water, water that runs off from the making of
dough, שמן זית, shemen zayit, olive oil, ומלח, u'melach, and salt. Somehow
you mix it together. רב יימר אמר, Rav Yeimar amar, it doesn't
sound like it's gonna help for a vitamin C
deficiency. What? No leafy green vegetables. Okay,
yeah, so okay. רב יימר אמר, Rav Yeimar amar, שעור גופיה, se'or
gufeih, שמן זית ומלח. shemen zayit u'melach. No, not the water from
the dough, but the actual dough. רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar,
משחא דגדפא דאווזא, mishcha d'gadpa d'avaza, the oil of the fat of
the wing of a, of a goose, of a goose wing.
So גדפא gadpa is a wing?
Yeah. Okay, I don't know how any of this is going to
solve a vitamin C deficiency. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, אנא עבדי לכולהו
ולא איתסי. ana avdi l'chulhu v'lo itsi. You know what? I tried
all those things and it didn't do me any good, I did
not get healed. עד דאמר לי ההוא טייעא, ad d'amar li hahu
taya'a, until a certain Arab said to me, אייתי קשייתא דזיתא, aytei
kashyata d'zeita, take the pits of olives דלא מלו תילתא d'lo malu
tilta that are, that are not yet a third ripe, וקלינהו בנורא,
v'kalinhu b'nura, burn the olive pits in a fire, אמרחא חדתא, amarcha
chadata, on a new shovel, ואדביק בככי דדרי, v'advik b'kakei d'dari, and
then take the paste that's made from it and put it on
your gum, ככי, kakei, the, on the gums of your teeth. So
עבדי הכי, avdi hachi, I did that, ואיתסאי, v'itsai, and I got
better. Okay, ממאי הוי? mimai havei? Now where do you get scurvy
from? מחמימי חמימי דחיטי, mechamimi chamimi d'cheiti, from eating overly hot wheaten
bread, ומשייורי כסא דהרסנא, u'mishiyurei kasa d'harsana, and from leftover fish hash.
So that's where you get scurvy. How do we know this is
scurvy? I don't know. Is this the scurvy that we, it's like
צרעת, tzara'at, like it's not, I have no idea. I only know
it's scurvy because that's what Artscroll says, צפדינא. tzafdina. That makes it
reasonable. Teeth, blood, gums? Well, the bleeding of gums, yeah, is that
what one of the symptoms is, the bleeding of gums? That's when
you lose your teeth. That's the beginning, then it goes to the
throat. Oh, well, we haven't got up to the throat yet, hold
on. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, okay, ומאי סימניה? u'mai
simaneih? And now it's going to say, what are the symptoms, what
are the signs of it? כד רמי מידי בככי, kad rami midi
b'kakei, when you put something in your teeth, ואתא דמא, v'ata dama,
and you bleed. So it's basically you have bleeding gums. מבי דרי,
mibei dari, and blood comes out of your gums. רבי יוחנן כי
חש בצפדינא, Rabbi Yochanan ki chash b'tzafdina, when Rabbi Yochanan had this
scurvy, which is what we said started the... with רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan scurvy, עבד הכי בשבתא ואיתסי. avad hachi beshabasa veitsei. So here
we have the violation of שבת. Shabbos. He went and he did
this, presumably, well maybe he did what the מטרוניתא matronisa said to
him, who knows which of these health things he now did. But
whichever one he did, he did it on שבת Shabbos even if
it involved the violation of שבת Shabbos and it actually healed him.
Okay. Yes. Okay, רבי יוחנן היכי עביד הכי? Rabbi Yochanan heichi avid
hachi? Now how did רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan do this? אמר רב
נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, wait did I skip
a line? No, שאני צפידנא, shani tzapidna, meaning the גמרא Gemara is
assuming that like what why are we assuming it's life-threatening? Now presumably
the reason why shouldn't we assume it's life-threatening? Well, one reason may
be is because the גמרא, Gemara, this is getting us back to
the beginning of the משנה, Mishna, where רב מתיא בן חרש Rav
Masya ben Charash says that if you've got some type of a
throat problem, you can take a medicine. So the גמרא Gemara is
assuming maybe the חכמים Chachamim disagree, maybe they felt the things that
were in the mouth and in the throat weren't life-threatening. So how
did רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan do this? So אמר רב נחמן בר
יצחק שאני צפידנא הואיל ומתחיל בפה וגומר בבני מעיים. Amar Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak shani tzapidna ho'il umaschil bepeh vegomer bivnei mei'ayim. No, things
that scurvy begins in the in the mouth and but it then
goes down the throat and it gets into the inner intestines, so
it is life-threatening and therefore you can do things even on שבת.
Shabbos. אמר ליה רב חייא בר אבא לרבי יוחנן, Amar lei Rav
Chiya bar Abba le'Rabbi Yochanan, so רב חייא בר אבא Rav Chiya
bar Abba said to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, כמאן כרבי מתיא בן
חרש? Keman k'Rabbi Masya ben Charash? So this is going this idea
that mouth and throat issues are life-threatening is going like רבי מתיא
בן חרש Rabbi Masya ben Charash דאמר חושש בפיו מטילים לו סם
בשבת, de'amar chochesh befiv matilin lo sam beShabbos, that somebody who has
some throat problem can be make a medicine on שבת. Shabbos. So
isn't that debated? So why are we assuming that רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan that that how could רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan be going like
that? So אמר ליה שאני אומר דזו ולא אחרת. Amar lei shani
omer dezu velo acheres. I say no that the rabbis only argue
with רב מתיא בן חרש Rav Masya ben Charash in this one
and not in the other. רב מתיא בן חרש Rav Masya ben
Charash said two things. He mentioned about the rabid dog and the
liver and he mentioned the throat. So the rabbis only argue on
him with the rabid dog. They actually agree to his point that
if you've got a sore throat you can make a medicine and
take it on שבת. Shabbos. And by the way in general when
we know that also very interesting which I'm not going to get
into, I mean obviously we're touching on it, but how הלכה, halacha,
you know how do you again the same question we sort of
dealt with yesterday, what type of of illness or disease or complication
do we identify as a potential פיקוח נפש? pikuach nefesh? So to
some degree it's ask the doctors.
But to some degree also the גמרא Gemara gives parameters.
I mean mostly it's ask the doctors, but the
גמרא Gemara also gives parameters. And one parameter the גמרא Gemara basically
has is anything that's basically from the gums in.
That anything in the mouth and starting in the gums in is
seen
as potentially life-threatening because
maybe that it can then get into your inner system. Or anyway,
so that's an important principle in פיקוח נפש. pikuach nefesh. Yes. You
always do those things on that principle and
not on the principle of eating the ashes of the cat or
something. Right, so that's an interesting question exactly. Meaning why right. Right.
So there is that whole issue about you know I think it's
true that basically without making too much of a הלכה halacha statement
here, but basically I can't speak for the חרדי Chareidi community, maybe
I think this is true for them as well, but
I think basically mostly
it goes by
the assessment of doctors not by what some formal thing in the
גמרא. Gemara.
But in some gray areas where you have these anxieties and this
and that but you really wonder is it really פיקוח נפש pikuach
nefesh or not? But the גמרא Gemara puts it in the פיקוח
נפש pikuach nefesh category. We allow that to sort of tip the
scales. Like one example which we're going to see is the גמרא
Gemara is basically going to say in the עמוד ב amud beis
that if somebody is locked in a room you can violate שבת
Shabbos to break down the door because you're just afraid that they're
going to be like scared to death. Now really? Like I mean
unless how is that a real פיקוח נפש? pikuach nefesh? So nevertheless
though, you can imagine you got a kid locked in a room
on שבת Shabbos and they really are getting very very scared and
are being hysterical or whatever. So how much does you say well
look at the bottom end of the day the גמרא Gemara calls
it פיקוח נפש. pikuach nefesh. So it's like those types of issues
I think that the basic approach is fundamentally you sort of say
based on our medical knowledge. But it's important to know what those
גמרא Gemara categories are sometimes if you need to rely on them.
Yeah all these remedies however we might evaluate them are really with
actual preparation. The actual like mixing and the boiling, the burning. I've
read, I've seen, I know opinions that if someone has a headache
they won't on שבת Shabbos they will not take a readily prepared
aspirin. Okay, so that issue I'll just say one word about that.
The גמרא Gemara says you don't do רפואה refua on שבת. Shabbos.
And the גמרא Gemara frames it, the בבלי Bavli frames it, probably
has a different reason historically, but the בבלי Bavli frames it as
a concern that you'll come to grind medicine. Now the question is
how can you say you don't do רפואה refua if we have
all these גמרא Gemara that basically say that even חילול שבת דאורייתא
chilul Shabbos De'oraisa you do for פיקוח נפש? pikuach nefesh? So basically
what develops is a tax... Taxonomy or hierarchy of different types of
illnesses. פיקוח נפש, pikuach nefesh, you violate שבת Shabbos דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, even
a דאורייתא d'Oraisa violation. If it's a case which is called חולה
כל גופו, choleh kol gufo, which means your whole body feels ill,
you have to lie down or it's something that is such like
this splitting headache or something so bad that in theory you would
be prepared to lie down even if it's on
a local part
of your body but you'd want to just go lie down. So
then we say that that you can do not דאורייתות d'Oraisas for
but דרבננות. d'Rabbannans. And it's a question what type of דרבננות. d'Rabbannans.
אמירה לעכו"ם Amira l'akum definitely. Can you directly do a דרבנן? d'Rabbanan?
But anyway, a range of דרבננות d'Rabbannans is allowed for חולה כל
גופו. choleh kol gufo. The smallest category is called, yeah, including taking
medicines, of course. The category that we apply this issue to about
just where it's the opposite, not that we allow things but we
disallow things, is the category called מיחוש בעלמא mishush b'alma where it's
not like you've got or it's like it's localized, it's just an
irritation, it's not like pervasive. And that's where we say this איסור
דרבנן issur d'Rabbanan of taking a medicine applies. That being said, a
number of פוסקים poskim say, I mean they're bothered by two things.
Number one is nowadays the concern that you'll grind your own medicine
is pretty much non-existent. And although normally that doesn't mean that a
דרבנן d'Rabbanan goes away just because the reasons fall away. But number
two, it like completely goes against the experience of Shabbat and completely
goes against everything else that's being articulated here, which is not just
about life, but if you apply it to חולה כל גופו, choleh
kol gufo, it's just about alleviating distress and suffering and so on.
Also allows latitude and here we're making it more difficult. So as
a result of which, some פוסקים poskim interpret the category of מיחוש
בעלמא mishush b'alma extremely, extremely narrowly and are pretty ready to include
most illnesses in the חולה כל גופו choleh kol gufo type of
a category. So that is an approach of many פוסקים. poskim. Yeah,
who knows, something like that. But then of course, I'll just end
by this saying from Rav Soloveitchik was known to have said, I
can't attest to this directly, that somebody asked him about like medicine
on שבת. Shabbos. He says, look, he says, if you really need
it, then you're a חולה כל גופו, choleh kol gufo, so it's
מותר. mutar. If you don't really need it, then it's not really
medicine, so it's also מותר. mutar. Alright, anyway, moving on. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, so תניא אומר בזו ולא באחרת.
Tanya omer b'zo v'lo b'acheres. In this one, either in this one
the rabid dog is where they argue, or Rashi says the other
way. In this one, the case by the throat problem, the rabbis
agree to him. Either way, it's saying the rabid dog is where
they debate, by the throat everybody agrees. So the גמרא Gemara says
לימא מסייע ליה, leima mesayei lei, let me come try to bring
a proof to this. מי שאחזו ירקון מאכילין אותו בשר חמור, Mi
she'achazo yerakon machilin oto basar chamor, somebody who is seized by jaundice,
you can feed him donkey meat. מי שנשך כלב שוטה מאכילין אותו
מחצר כבד שלו, Mi shenashach kelev shotah machilin oto mechatzar kaved shelo,
if he's bit by a rabid dog, you feed him from the
lobe of the liver of the dog. והחושש בפיו מטילין לו סם
בשבת, V'hachoshash b'piv matilin lo sam b'Shabbos, and if somebody has a
throat problem, you give him a medicine on שבת. Shabbos. דברי רבי
מתיא בן חרש. Divrei Rebbe Matya ben Charash. That's what Rebbe Matya
ben Charash says. So the two we had in the משנה Mishna
plus this one about the jaundice. וחכמים אומרים באלו אין בהם משום
רפואה. V'chachamim omrim b'elu ein bahem mishum refuah. Those do not have
רפואה. refuah. Now those would seem to mean all those three. But
the גמרא Gemara interestingly assumes אלו elu means what you are saying,
the treatments that you are saying are not genuine treatments. And therefore
you cannot do it. Not that the illnesses aren't illnesses, but the
treatments are not legitimate treatments. Maybe you could do something else if
it could really work. Those things are not treatments. So the גמרא
Gemara says באלו, b'elu, so it assumes the word באלו b'elu means
not all of those three, but some of those three. I have
no idea why it's reading that. למעוטי מאי, Limutei mai, so which
ones are they identifying is not a genuine therapeutic and which ones
would they be okay with? מאי לאו למעוטי סם, Mai lav limutei
sam, maybe it means what they're saying is that this remedy for
the jaundice and the rabid dog are not real remedies, but the
medicine for the sore throat would be. So doesn't, isn't that what
they mean? So they agree with the sore throat. So the גמרא
Gemara says לא למעוטי מקיזין דם לסרונכי. Lo limutei makizin dam l'sarunchi.
No, we're going to have because there's another thing we see that
gets discussed, which is whether you can let blood for סרונכי, sarunchi,
which is, I forget how they translate סרונכי sarunchi there. I looked
it up, I forgot. Exclude regulating blood to heal quinsy? Quinsy? Isn't
that what they used to, a cop show, Quincy Adams? Q-U-I-N-S-Y. Okay,
anyway, I don't know. Jastrow said something else. Alright, anyway. הכי נמי
מסתברא, Hachi nami mistabra, that makes sense that maybe it's the bloodletting
that they are okay with. דתניא תנו רבנן שלשה דברים אמר רבי
ישמעאל ברבי יוסי ששמע משום רבי מתיא בן חרש. D'tanya tnu rabanan
shelosha devarim amar Rebbe Yishmael b'Rebbe Yosi she'shama mishum Rebbe Matya ben
Charash. So now it's a tradition from Rebbe Matya ben Charash. מקיזין
דם לסרונכי Makizin dam l'sarunchi you let blood for this סרונכי sarunchi
problem בשבת. b'Shabbos. ומי שנשך כלב שוטה מאכילין אותו מחצר כבד שלו,
U-mi shenashach kelev shotah machilin oto mechatzar kaved shelo, for the rabid
dog you give the lobe of the liver. והחושש בפיו מטילין לו
סם בשבת, V'hachoshash b'piv matilin lo sam b'Shabbos, and somebody's got. sore
throat, you do some medicine into, you drink some medicine. וחכמים אומרים
באלו אין בהם משום רפואה. va-chachamim omrim be-elu ein bahem mishum refuah.
Those, assuming now those means some of those, don't have, are not
real remedies. באלו למעוטי מאי, be-elu le-ma'utei mai, so which ones are
our remedies and which ones are not? מאי לאו אטרתי בתרייתא? mai
lav a-tertei batraita? You're saying that the last two, the issue about
the sore throat and the rabid dog are not real remedies. ולמעוטי
דרישא, u-le-ma'utei de-reisha, but the first one, the bloodletting for this סרונכי,
serunchi, is a remedy. So you see that it's סרונכי serunchi that
they concede to, not the sore throat. גמרא Gemara says no, לא,
lo, maybe the opposite. אטרתי דרישא וקמייתא, a-tertei de-reisha ve-kamyata, maybe the
first two are not real remedies, the bloodletting and the rabid dog,
ולמעוטי דסיפא, u-le-ma'utei de-seifa, but the last one is a remedy, the
case about the sore throat. Okay, so basically what we're trying to
say is that the rabbis agree with the sore throat, that you
can do various types of remedies, and their debate is by these
other remedies. תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear, top of eighty-four
B. דתני רב בר שמואל, de-tani Rav Bar Shmuel, עוברה שהריחה מאכילין
אותה עד שתשוב נפשה. ubarah she-hericha ma'achilin otah ad she-tashuv nafshah. So
here we have another ברייתא: Baraita: the pregnant woman that got a
smell, you feed her until she calms down. ומי שנשכו כלב שוטה
מאכילין אותו מחצר כבד שלו, u-mi she-neshacho kelev shoteh ma'achilin oto me-chatzer
keved shelo, the rabid dog you feed the lobe of the liver.
והחושש בפיו מטילים לו סם בשבת, ve-ha-choshesh be-fiv matilin lo sam be-Shabbat,
and a sore throat you give some medicine into, you drink some
medicine on שבת. Shabbat. דברי divrei רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי Rabbi Elazar
be-Rabbi Yossi שאמר משום רב מתיא בן חרש. she-amar mishum Rav Matya
ben Charash. So that's the tradition of רב מתיא בן חרש. Rav
Matya ben Charash. וחכמים אומרים va-chachamim omrim and the sages say, בזו
ולא באחרת, be-zu ve-lo be-acheret, only this and not others. So בזו
אהיי, be-zu a-hei, which one are they conceding to? Anyway, by the
way, because of this ברייתא Baraita where they concede בזו, be-zu, this
shows you that's what that's why the גמרא Gemara initially... because as
Michael said, why are we assuming they concede about anything? It sounds
like they're arguing about all of it. But in this ברייתא Baraita
they say, okay, with that I'll concede to you. So that's what
led us to our whole assumption before in trying to identify which
is the one case that the חכמים Chachamim concede to. So בזו
אהיי, be-zu a-hei, which is the one they concede to? אילימא ilima
עוברה, ubarah, if it's the pregnant woman, פשיטא, peshita, עוברה מי איכא
למאן דאמר דלא? ubarah mi ika le-man de-amar de-lo? A pregnant woman,
everybody agrees that the case of the pregnant woman needs to be
fed. So they wouldn't have to say with this I concede to
you, although it's pretty funny why not? He said it, so they
want to point out that they agree to that one. Anyway, אלא
לאו אסם, ela lav a-sam, it must be if they're conceding to
one and they don't have to concede to the pregnant woman, and
we know they disagree about the rabid dog, so the only third
one he mentioned was the throat medicine. So clearly they're saying they
concede, it shows they're conceding about the throat medicine. שמע מינה, shema
mina, that's a good point, the sages concede to that. רב אשי
אמר מתניתין נמי דיקא, Rav Ashi amar matnitin nami dika, it's also
implicit in our משנה, Mishnah, because our משנה Mishnah says that רב
מתיא בן חרש Rav Matya ben Charash says you feed the... the
rabbis say you don't feed the lobe of the liver... liver. רב
מתיא בן חרש Rav Matya ben Charash says you do feed the
lobe of the liver of the rabid dog. And then the משנה
Mishnah goes on to say, ועוד אמר רב מתיא בן חרש, ve-od
amar Rav Matya ben Charash, החושש בפיו מטילים לו סם בשבת. ha-choshesh
be-fiv matilin lo sam be-Shabbat. After the liver discussion and the rabid
dog, it says oh by the way רב מתיא בן חרש Rav
Matya ben Charash also says you can take medicine for a sore
throat on שבת. Shabbat. ולא פליגי רבנן עליה ve-lo pligi rabanan aleih
and there was and that was not followed by a dissenting view
of the rabbis. ואי איתא דפליגי רבנן עליה, ve-i ita de-pligi rabanan
aleih, and if the rabbis argued on both the cases, the rabid
dog and the throat, לערבינהו וליתנינהו, le-arvinhu u-le-taninhu, put them together. Say
רב מתיא בן חרש Rav Matya ben Charash says here's what you
do for a rabid dog and here's what you do for a
sore throat, and the rabbis say you can't do it. But no,
we framed it as a debate about the rabid dog and then
we mentioned his position about the throat. So ליתנינהו וליפלגי רבנן בסיפא,
litaninhu u-lifligi rabanan be-seifa, so why not just put them all together
and have the rabbis argue at the end on everything? So שמע
מינה, shema mina, since they didn't do it, since the argument was
only at the rabid dog stage and then afterwards it was followed
by the statement about the throat and nobody disagreed, it sounds like
the throat is a point that everyone concedes to. Which by the
way is nice, in addition to the just point about the throat,
because רב מתיא בן חרש Rav Matya ben Charash when he talks
about the throat says you have if somebody has a sore throat
you have them drink this medicine, and then he says because it's
a פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh and ספק נפשות safek nefashot and any
ספק נפשות safek nefashot is דוחה את השבת. docheh et ha-Shabbat. So
this way that general line, that principle, right? Which was said so
nice and clearly in that statement, is now not just his opinion,
but now is actually consensus opinion. I mean not like we ever
doubted the principle, but it was a little ironic that that whole
basic statement of principle was said by רב מתיא בן חרש Rav
Matya ben Charash and wasn't stated in a very general way. So
now we're actually saying that that second part of רב מתיא בן
חרש's Rav Matya ben Charash statement is a consensus opinion. Is this
regarded as the Talmudic source for the principle, this סוגיה? Sugya? Well,
in our... yeah I mean all of our משניות, Mishnayot, but that
line is the very clear line, but it comes up, I mean
it's going to be with the building falling down, it's all of
these סוגיות. Sugyas. Okay, so מפני שספק נפשות הוא, mipnei she-safek nefashot
hu, because it is a risk to life and this is then
the principle in the משנה, Mishnah, and any risk of life overrides
שבת. Shabbat. So למה לי למימרא וכל ספק נפשות דוחה את השבת?
lama li le-meimra ve-chol ספק נפשות docheh et ha-Shabbat? Why do you
have to say because it's a risk to life and every risk
of life overrides שבת? Shabbat? I mean it's what you've been saying
all along. Do this, do this, do that, why do you have
to say it again that way? אמר רב יהודה אמר רב amar
Rav Yehuda amar Rav to tell you... to tell you the following:
לא ספק שבת זו בלבד אמרו אלא אפילו ספק שבת אחרת. Lo
safek Shabbat zo bilvad amru ella afilu safek Shabbat acheret. Even if
it's not only about this שבת, Shabbat, but even about another שבת.
Shabbat. Meaning what? היכי דמי? Heichi dami? What's the case? כגון דאמדו
ליה תמניא יומי. Kegon d'amdu lei tamnaya yomei. They basically said this
guy is going to need to do a certain medicine, you know,
a certain type of a thing for eight days straight. ויומא קמא
שבתא. Vi'yoma kama Shabsah. And the first day is שבתא. Shabsah. So
מהו דתימא לעכב עד לאורתא כי היכי דלא נחל ליה תרי שבתות.
Mahu d'teima l'akeiv ad l'urta ki heichi d'lo neicheil lei t'rei Shabsos.
So you know what, why not start the whole process on Sunday,
Saturday night? Because anyway that way it'll only be one week, one
violation of שבת, Shabbat, not two, because it's going to go eight
days, it'll include next שבת. Shabbat. So let's try to minimize it
and maybe again if it's going to take eight days, maybe there's
not a sense of like urgency, like if you don't do it
now he's going to die. So there's not an urgency and you
could maybe say we'll start tomorrow. Nevertheless, קא משמע לן kamashmalan that
no, right now he is, he does have a life-threatening issue and
you start it as soon as possible. You don't start making חשבונות
cheshbonos of well, he's not going to die right away and you
know big deal we'll wait a few hours. No. If he's in
a פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh situation, you deal what needs to be
done immediately, you don't start making חשבונות cheshbonos to you know push
things off till after שבת. Shabbat. Okay. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami
hachi, so we talk similarly, מחממין חמין לחולה בשבת. mechammin chammin l'choleh
b'Shabbat. You heat up hot water for a sick person on שבת,
Shabbat, בין להשקותו bein l'hashkoto whether to drink the hot water, בין
להברותו bein l'havroto whether to basically like bathe him in the hot
water to give him strength by the bath. ולא שבת זו בלבד
אמרו Vi'lo Shabbat zo bilvad amru and not only if it's like
urgent like you have to do it now or he's going to
die, אלא לשבת אחרת, ella l'Shabbat acheret, even if it's something that
basically is going to stretch on until next שבת Shabbat and it's
an ongoing type of a thing, you don't you know you don't
push it off, you do what you know you do what needs
to be done now even if it's not even if it's not
like he's about to die right now. Is that bath considered taking
a bath, right? Is that considered like just helping his person? Well
look, so what's not being said black and white here is a
principle of עושים כל צרכי חולה בשבת, osin kol tzorchei choleh b'Shabbat,
which means you don't determine by every little thing that you're about
to do, if I don't do this will his life be at
risk? Basically, if once a person is in a status of פיקוח
נפש, pikuach nefesh, you take care of all of his health needs.
Okay. Obviously the larger חשבון cheshbon is that if you don't take
care of some of the health needs, it obviously increases the level
of risk, but you don't have to make that חשבון cheshbon wait
a minute you mean to tell me if he's not going to
bathe he's actually going to be in a greater risk situation? You
don't say that. You say this guy is סכנת נפשות, sakanat nefashot,
פיקוח נפש, pikuach nefesh, he has a life-threatening illness, you do what
you do anything related to taking care of his health needs. That's
a very important principle, עושים כל צרכי חולה. osin kol tzorchei choleh.
So there is a little bit of that question but again, you
know part of it does have to do, I mean there's a
discussion about this, part of it does have to do with the
חשבון cheshbon that any, you know that any little thing related to
just to you know to his health factors in to to some
possible you know question of פיקוח נפש. pikuach nefesh. That's one way
of thinking about it. Or it could be a הותרה hutra type
of an idea. You know and it is a question of exactly
how you define the parameters of what does it mean everything he
needs, you know? So, but, but anyway, but that's part of the
point and it's important to raise it here, you're right, about what
does that mean a bath, what does it mean hot water. So
it doesn't have to mean like oh my god if you don't
do this he's going to die. He's sick, he's פיקוח נפש, pikuach
nefesh, you do what he needs needs to be done for the
sake of his health. ולא שבת זו בלבד אמרו אלא לשבת אחרת.
Vi'lo Shabbat zo bilvad amru ella l'Shabbat acheret. ואין ממתינים לו שמא
יברי, Vi'ein mamtinim lo shema yavri, you don't say ah well you
know let's see maybe if we wait maybe he'll recover, maybe he
won't need us to heat up the hot water, אלא מחממין לו
מיד. ella mechammin lo miyad. You right now there's a concern, you
take care of it now. You don't try to do any waiting
games and any חשבונות, cheshbonos, מפני שספק נפשות דוחה את השבת. mipnei
shesafek nefashot docheh et haShabbat. Any doubt of life overrides שבת. Shabbat.
ולא ספק שבת זו אלא אפילו שבת אחרת, Vi'lo safek Shabbat zo
ella afilu Shabbat acheret, not only this שבת, Shabbat, it's a little
bit repetitive here, even a next שבת. Shabbat. ואין עושים דברים הללו
Vi'ein osim devarim hallalu and you don't do these things לא על
ידי נכרים lo al yedei nochrim ולא על ידי כותים vi'lo al
yedei Kutim or as he probably corrects this קטנים. Ketanim. You don't
say hey let's do it in a way that there won't have
to be a חילול שבת. chilul Shabbat. Let's get a non-Jew to
do it. Let's get a minor to do it. Okay? No, you
don't try to hand it off to other people, אלא על ידי
גדולי ישראל. ella al yedei gedolei Yisrael. But by the גדלים. gedolim.
No, but that means a Jewish adult, doesn't necessarily mean גדולי הדור,
gedolei haDor, but it basically means don't try to get minors, don't
try to get non-Jews, Jewish adults, you do it and you don't
try to minimize. Now why not? Why not say hey let's try
to do it, I mean if it does, if it can easily
be done by the non-Jew, if I can get the non-Jew to
drive the guy to the hospital, why should I drive the guy
to the hospital? So take a look at תוספות, Tosafot, אלא על
ידי גדולי ישראל. ella al yedei gedolei Yisrael. תוספות Tosafot says ואפילו
היכא דאפשר בנכרי מצוה בישראל שמא יתעצל הנכרי ולא יעשה ויבא לידי
סכנה. va'afilu heicha d'efshar b'nochri mitzvah b'Yisrael shema yitatzel hanochri vi'lo ya'aseh
vi'yavo lidei sakana. Because you, you know, maybe we'll assume that if
you do it by an adult and an adult you understand the
importance of פיקוח נפש. pikuach nefesh. You are going to apply the
don't trust something so important to somebody else. Wait, why not? Because
if you understand the full importance of it, right, you don't want
to trust anybody else. Now, the other person... All right, you know
what? They're not going to appreciate the urgency. The whole point is
we appreciate the urgency because we're being ready to be מחלל שבת
mechallel Shabbos. *mechallel Shabbat* for פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh *pikuach nefesh*. So
we've completely internalized that. So תוספות *Tosafot* just makes it sound like,
yeah, this guy, like I've been sort of saying right now, won't
really internalize fully the urgency of פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh. *pikuach nefesh*.
If you had a guy that totally would, you had a taxi
driver that, whatever, that I'll give you an extra fifty if you
get there within the next twenty minutes or whatever, so it wouldn't
be a problem. But there's another explanation about why even if this
one guy will do just as good of a job, you should
not be looking for giving it to a non-Jew or a minor,
which is why? What? Well, you're doing the מצווה *mitzvah* and also
the larger policy point because if people see, oh look, I tried
to get a non-Jew, even if in this case there was no
trade-off, the message that gets sent in is that this is problematic
and you should find ways to get around it and to minimize
it, and that's going to lead in the future to hesitation, to
not doing it as well, and the message has to be no
hesitation. Yes? Yes, because this happened to me, my wife was pregnant,
felt labor, whatever it is, on שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*. Right. So should
I have, like, forget to call the cab, and I should have...
So that's an interesting question about the whole issue about pregnancy and
labor and so on is because at what stage is it פיקוח
נפש pikuach nefesh. *pikuach nefesh*? At this stage is it right now
when you're starting to get contractions or whatever, is it already פיקוח
נפש pikuach nefesh *pikuach nefesh*? I actually tell people there, so again,
you could say are you being too מחמיר *machmir* on פיקוח נפש
*pikuach nefesh*, are you being מחמיר *machmir* on שבת Shabbos. *Shabbat*? What
I tell people is I said, look, if I were to tell
you, let's say you say, as soon as my wife goes into
labor, I'm going to jump into the car or whatever, I said
if I told you I'll give you a hundred bucks and I'll
pay for a cab if you do a cab, would you take
me up on the offer? You would say no, I want to
be the one to drive her. So if you say no, I
want to be the one to drive her, then fine, you should
drive her. But if you would take my hundred bucks and take
my offer to pay a cab for you, then how much, then
it's not really yet at that stage of urgency. But you could
say I'm being too מחמיר *machmir* on שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*, but that's
in a case where there's a long process before, could be, sometimes
it happens before you're ready, but it's not yet at that stage.
I would not say such a thing if somebody ממש mamash *mamash*
is in an accident. I wouldn't for a second say, oh, figure
out would I be willing to hire a cab and am I
just, no. If somebody's in an accident, there's a real sort of
thing right now, you just do immediately what needs to be done.
Yes. How localized, how localized can the condition be? For example, on
שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*, let's say someone's got an infection on their hand.
Right. It's localized. Right. But you've got to keep on applying the
antibiotic ointment on שבת *Shabbat*. I'm not going to get into all
of the parameters about that. That's, that's the question. Yeah, but clearly
things that if you don't attend to them, there's an element of
risk. Look, there's also a הלכה halacha *halachah*, for example, that if
it's only a סכנת איבר *sakanat eiver* and not a סכנת נפשות
*sakanat nefashot*, we don't biblically violate שבת *Shabbat* except in practice what
we wind up saying is anything that's a סכנת איבר *sakanat eiver*
is essentially a סכנת נפשות *sakanat nefashot* and we sort of make
that whole category essentially moot. But yes, that's the whole question of
what you put in that category. Once something is פיקוח נפש *pikuach
nefesh*, childbirth is an interesting, it's like the רמב"ם *Rambam* says it's
כפיקוח נפש *k'pikuach nefesh*, exactly what stage of the childbirth we're talking
about. But a thing that's like an immediate emergency then you don't
do any of this hesitation, partly because not just because you won't
do it so well if you try to get a non-Jew, but
partly because of the larger policy point that you have to be...
other ראשונים *Rishonim* a lot say that, that you have to make
it clear that you do it without hesitation. Yes. But just this
thing specifically, you seem to be taking a different approach with pregnancy.
I was waiting to be attacked about me being a very unfeminist
male thing to be saying... The other, what we've been talking about
until now is general, a person's life is at risk, you don't
need to have exactly the details and so on. But here you're
taking a different approach. Well, again, the only question is the point
about the difference between if the contractions have just... No, the question
is at what stage. I'm not saying like as a, I shouldn't,
I don't want to be misinterpreted, I mean my God, the very
first example the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* had was the pregnant woman who
needs to be fed or whatever. I just mean that at like
the early stages of contractions, is that already, we're not there yet.
Yeah, that's, I'm sorry if that wasn't clear, that's all I was
saying, I was just saying that when people get ready to go
to the hospital, sometimes it's just very early in on the process.
Once it becomes more urgent, yeah, I'm not talking about that. Okay,
so those people don't really need to worry about that then. What?
Go by myself, what you're saying. Yeah, but, or shouldn't go, but
this whole discussion of פיקוח נפש *pikuach nefesh* assumes Jews. You are
exactly going to be... That'll be in two days from now we'll
talk about that. Okay, about non-Jews. Alright, moving on. Okay. Okay. ואין
אומרים or maybe that's even tomorrow. That's I think that's tomorrow. That's
tomorrow the whole non-Jew system. So it's good it won't be recorded.
All right anyway. All right. I have to All right well I'll
have to therefore say because it won't be recorded so I'll say
now for the record a great a great story you know because
the whole question is according to the Mishnah as we saw if
a building falls on somebody and you know it's a non-Jew actually
we're going to get to it a little bit at the bottom
of today's well we'll see if we get there in a few
minutes. Anyway, if you know it's a non-Jew you don't you're not
מחלל שבת. mechallel Shabbos You know? But that then leads to like
a question is that really how we פוסק? pasken? You know? So
the המאירי haMeiri says no he was only talking about those like
pagans they were immoral of course you're מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbos for
the life of a non-Jew. That's the המאירי's haMeiri opinion which is
the more sort of you know radical in the sense of changing
the basic categories one you know in terms of how the גמרא
Gemara. frames it but one that obviously people are attracted to you
know some people are very attracted to nowadays in terms of sort
of the you know the basic sort of you know moral position
that it lays out. Rav Moshe's approach is more to say that
well you can always stay be מחלל שבת to save the life
of a non-Jew because it's an indirect saving of the life of
a Jew because if you don't it exposes Jews to danger and
to risk and so on and sometimes you know that's also referred
to in a different way as like you know because of משום
איבה mishum eivah or מפני דרכי שלום mipnei darchei shalom but in
a way that's so much of a concern of risk of life
you know to not only does it make them angry at us
but it ממש is an element of risk so we do it
really to save our lives which gets you the same result but
it does it indirectly through without shifting the categories which unfortunately has
now the negative side effect which is that you know this like
that's the principle on which הצלה Hatzalah answers calls on שבת for
for non-Jews but Rav Moshe made a very much clear point of
saying even if you think nobody is going to find out if
you don't respond nevertheless there's always an there's always this concern this
איבה eivah concern whatever and you always have to respond. Yeah basically
because eventually people will find out and the word will get around
and what have you. Anyway the point is yes but the point
is that apparently there are one or two הצלות Hatzalahs I've heard
of ברוך השם Baruch Hashem not the one in Riverdale that do
make a bit of a חשבון cheshbon like how much will it
be known if they don't respond. Here. Here? The what there was
a הצלה Hatzalah they didn't respond to a call? Yeah years ago
before Rav Yosef Kanetzky was around. Wow. This guy in a gas
station on the highway called הצלה Hatzalah they wouldn't come he called
911. Wow. Wow. So it's a big issue that you know it's
not exactly that Rav Moshe gets you to the same result because
even though Rav Moshe tries to make to make it that every
case counts this way once that's the sort of rationale there's a
question about somebody making that type of a חשבון. cheshbon. So there's
a story anyway that that what's his name Professor Saul Lieberman was
he was very close friends with this non-Jewish philosopher who like you
know is very noble but did Jewish stuff I'm trying to remember
who it was. I'm not remembering the name of the guy anyway
so they were walking in the street once on שבת. So the
guy said and you know with also some of the JTS students
were there so anyway this non-Jewish colleague said so if that building
were to fall on me on שבת would you would you you
know would you violate שבת to save my life? So he said
yes of course. So he said he said would you do it
because it's the הלכה halacha. or would you do it because of
דרכי שלום? darchei shalom? Or you know so he said no I
would do it because it's the הלכה. halacha? So he was satisfied
he walked away and then his students turned to him and said
what do you mean? What do you mean it's הלכה? He says
nah I told him that for דרכי שלום. darchei shalom. All right
anyway. All right let's do a little bit more of the גמרא.
Gemara All right so okay ולא ידי נכרים ולא ידי קטנים אלא
ידי גדולי ישראל V'lo yedei nochrim v'lo yedei ktanim ella yedei gedolei
Yisrael by Jewish adult. You don't do it. ואין אומרים יעשו דברים
הללו V'ein omrim yaasu devarim halalu so stay here Rivka it's good
you're back today. Don't say do do these things לא על פי
נשים ולא על פי כותים lo al pi nashim v'lo al pi
Kutim not by women or Samaritans or non-Jews אלא מצטרפין לדעת אחרת
ella mitztarfin l'daas acheres they combine for another opinion. So what does
that mean? So Rashi says what it means is that if based
on the opinion of a woman or כותי Kuti or a non-Jew
whatever this person is פיקוח נפש and other people don't say that
then you don't trust her opinion and judge the person as פיקוח
נפש. But wait you're saying you don't say all that you don't
mean don't go do no according to Rashi do not go by
a woman's professional medical opinion that it's פיקוח נפש. But if there's
a debate two people say it is פיקוח נפש two people say
it isn't one and two or whatever it is then the woman
can add and be a corroborating testimony. Now the problem is number
one is first of all based on the earlier גמרא you didn't
need numbers right as long as you know any one opinion or
whatever based on any one against two two against many anyway you
didn't need numbers number one. Number two is as the Rosh says
he says why should we not trust a woman who knows medicine?
Why should her knowledge medical- now be any less trustworthy than a
man's? So he gives הרא"ש *HaRosh*, so he gives two alternative interpretations.
One is the exact opposite of what רש"י *Rashi* says, which is
don't discount what a woman says, but as long as, you know,
even if they are somehow going against the men doctors, if a
woman says it's פיקוח נפש *Pikuach Nefesh*, you listen to her. It's
a hard read in the language of the גמרא *Gemara*, but that's
what he tries to say. The alternative he says is, and this
is I think the way it's more interpreted להלכה *le-halacha*, which is
basically don't, one minute, now I totally forgot what it was. What
he says is don't say let it be done not by women.
Meaning, yes, do the women. Yeah, well that's more or less what
he said, although in a different way. But anyway, hold on one
second, I just want to tell you what he says, he says,
hold on, here. Oh, meaning like this, he says don't say, oh,
let's get a woman to do it. Let's get a woman to
drive him to the hospital, because this is sort of making a
sociological point. It's similar to the point before about get a non-Jew
or a minor. Even though for a woman it would still be,
you know, an observant woman would still be חילול שבת *chillul Shabbat*,
but people will think, oh yes, the men don't want to violate
so they're getting the women to do it. And that therefore leads
to again feeling that this is something that is problematic and it's
better for us men not to do it, we'll find someone else
to do it for us, and therefore don't have them do it,
not that there's a problem with them doing it, but sociologically that
will be read as a way of saying that it's not something
that we really should be doing, so let's get some flunky to
do it for us, let's get the women to do it for
us. Let's just say it won't use an air of insistence? Exactly,
like the guy will have his wife do the carrying. Rather he
says על פי *Al pi*? Yeah, so he switches the גרסא *girsa*
according to that instead of על פי *Al pi*, על ידי נשים
*Al Yedei Nashim*. There are different גרסאות *girsa'ot*. Let's read just a
little bit more, okay? I just want to get a little bit
to the תנו רבנן *Tanu Rabanan*. תנו רבנן, פיקוח נפש בשבת, הזריז
הרי זה משובח *Tanu Rabanan, Pikuach Nefesh b'Shabbat, ha-zariz harei zeh meshubach*.
The one who is zealous is praised. And the parallel of this
in the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* is that the one who delays and postpones
הרי זה שופך דמים *harei zeh shofech damim* is like a murderer.
Okay, so that's a very heavy alternative, but again don't hesitate. Okay?
Yeah, do whatever you need to. ואין צריך ליטול רשות מבית דין
*Ve-ein tzarich litol reshut mi-Beit Din*. Don't say, oh wait, let me
ask my רב *rav*. Okay. כיצד *Ketsad*, what's the scenario? ראה תינוק
שנפל לים *Ra'ah tinok she-nafal l'yam*, if you saw an infant fall
into the ocean, פורש מצודה ומעלהו *pores metsuda u-ma'alehu*, you spread out
a net and you lift him up. והזריז הרי זה משובח ואין
צריך ליטול רשות מבית דין *Ve-ha-zariz harei zeh meshubach ve-ein tzarich litol
reshut mi-Beit Din*. So what does that double phrase mean, oh do
it quickly and don't even wait to ask? ואף על גב דצייד
כוורי *Ve-af al gav de-tzayid kveirei*, even if in the process you're
catching fish. Don't say, oh I gotta do it in a way
that I'm not catching fish. Forget it, just do it. ראה תינוק
שנפל לבור *Ra'ah tinok she-nafal l'bor*, you saw an infant fall into
the well, עוקר חוליא ומעלהו *oker hulya u-ma'alehu*, you can dig out
some dirt and bring it to get into it and bring him
up. חוליא *Hulya*, yeah. Yeah, but it's a clump of dirt. והזריז
הרי זה משובח ואין צריך ליטול רשות מבית דין *Ve-ha-zariz harei zeh
meshubach ve-ein tzarich litol reshut mi-Beit Din*. What does that language mean,
don't hesitate? אף על גב דמתקן דרגא *Af al gav de-metaken darga*,
even if by your digging you're making steps and you're making the
pit, you know, you're building it a better pit. Don't say, oh
let me figure out a way to do it that's not going
to do that. ראה שננעלה דלת בפני תינוק *Ra'ah she-ninalah dalt bifnei
tinok*, here's the idea of being locked in a room, a child
is locked in a room, שוברו ומוציאו *shovro u-motzi'o* והזריז הרי זה
משובח ואין צריך *ve-ha-zariz harei zeh meshubach ve-ein tzarich*... yeah, that he'll
be scared to death and that'll whatever, do... again, it's a little,
you know, yeah, ואין צריך ליטול רשות מבית דין *ve-ein tzarich litol
reshut mi-Beit Din*, I mentioned that before. ואף על גב דקמכוין למיתבר
בשיפי *Ve-af al gav de-kamkhavein l'mitbar bi-shifei*, this is interesting, even though
as you're breaking the door you're intending to get some wood chips.
Oh good, then I'll be able to use the wood chips after
שבת *Shabbat* for my firewood. So even though you're intending, it's not
a problem because your intent doesn't change your action. Okay. מכבין ומפסיקין
מפני הדליקה בשבת והזריז הרי זה משובח ואין צריך ליטול רשות מבית
דין *Mekhabin u-mafsikin mipnei ha-dleika b'Shabbat ve-ha-zariz harei zeh meshubach ve-ein tzarich
litol reshut mi-Beit Din*. You can put out a fire on שבת
*Shabbat* and you can put like vessels that will be a wall
against the fire, a firewall, and you don't and don't hesitate. So
what's the don't hesitate phrase? ואף על גב דקא מחריך *Ve-af al
gav de-kamakhreikh*, even though you are basically making hot embers and maybe
you'll want to use them for cooking on after שבת *Shabbat*. וצריכא
*U-tzrikha*, you need to tell me all cases. דאשמעינן ים משום דאהא
ואהא אזלי *De-ashmi'inan yam mishum de-aha v'aha azlei*. If it's the ocean,
you tell me okay don't wait to ask a שאלה *she'elah* because
by the time you ask your שאלה *she'elah* the baby is going
to float away or whatever. אבל בור דקא יתבי *Aval bor de-ka
yatvi*, but the pit, that the guy isn't going anywhere, let me
go ask my רב *rav* first. אימה לא *Eima lo*. וצריכא *Tzrikha*.
No, it doesn't matter, you don't wait, you don't hesitate. דאשמעינן בור
משום דקמיבעית *De-ashmi'inan bor mishum de-kamibat*, because... be scared at the bottom
of a well. אבל נעילת דלת *aval ne'ilat delet*, but if it's
a guy's just behind a locked door, אפשר דיתיב בהאי גיסא ומשבש
ליה באמגוזי *efshar d'yateiv b'hai gisa u'mishabesh lei b'amgozi*, maybe go sit
over at another side and play with like nuts, maybe entertain himself,
you know, how scared to death is he gonna be in a
room behind a door? Maybe it's not פיקוח נפש *pikuach nefesh*. צריכה
*tzericha*, so even that is פיקוח נפש *pikuach nefesh* and you do
not hesitate, you do it, you do it immediately without any hesitation.
Exactly. Yep. Okay. Does anybody say קדיש *kaddish*?